Guide to the Marion Belanger photographs, 2001-2012 RL.11615
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Marion Belanger photographs
2001-2012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Belanger, Marion, 1957-
RL.11615
2.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes 25 black-and-white and 48 color digital inkjet prints
Collection comprises 25 black-and-white and 48 color photographs taken from 2001 to 2012 by Marion Belanger, documenting the intersection of natural and human-built environments. Belanger's series "Everglades," taken in Florida between 2001-2004, presents images of wildlife and natural landscapes affected by the impacts of tourism, agriculture, migrant worker housing, construction, and activities of the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers and the U.S. Army. Her portfolio "Rift/Fault," shot between 2006-2012, documents zones in California and Iceland where the San Andreas Fault and the Mid-Atlantic Rift exist - visibly or invisibly - alongside human environments; subjects in this series include housing developments, monitoring stations, geologic features and landscapes, coastal roads, and geothermal structures such as greenhouses. The digital inkjet prints in both series measure 13 or 13 1/2 x16 inches. Both projects were published as photobooks (2009 and 2012, respectively). Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
25 black-and-white and 48 color digital inkjet prints
Biographical / Historical
Marion Belanger photographs the cultural landscape, particularly where geology and the built environment intersect. She was an honoree for the 2017 Shpilman International Prize for Excellence in Photography from the Israeli Museum of Art, and is the author of Rift/ Fault, with an essay by Lucy Lippard (Radius Books, 2016) and Everglades: Outside and Within, with an essay by Susan Orlean (Center for American Places at Columbia College Chicago, 2009). Belanger was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship to photograph the contested landscape of the Florida Everglades in 2002.
She earned an M.F.A. from the Yale University School of Art where she was the recipient of both the John Ferguson Weir Award and the Schickle-Collingwood Prize, and a B.F.A. from the College of Art & Design at Alfred University. She has been an artist in residence at the MacDowell Colony, Everglades National Park, and MASS MoCA, among others.
Her photographs are shown internationally, and her work is held in many collections including the National Gallery for Art, the New Orleans Museum of Art, and the Yale University Art Gallery and the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library. Exhibitions include Photography and America's National Parks, George Eastman Museum, Rochester, NY; Internationale Fototage: Contemporary American Photography, Mannheim, Germany; Northern (L) Attitudes: Norwegian and American Contemporary Art, The American-Scandinavian Foundation, New York, NY. The artist resides in Guilford, Connecticut and she teaches at the Hartford Art School.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes. All other uses require the permission of the photographer.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Marion Belanger photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2018 and 2019.
Scope and Contents
Collection comprises 25 black-and-white and 48 color photographs taken from 2001 to 2012 by Marion Belanger, documenting the intersection of natural and human-built environments.
Belanger's series "Everglades," taken in Florida between 2001-2004, presents black-and-white images of wildlife and natural landscapes affected by the impacts of tourism, agriculture, migrant worker housing, construction, and activities of the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers and the U.S. Army. This series was also published in 2009 as Everglades: Outside and Within.
Her portfolio "Rift/Fault," shot between 2006-2012, documents zones in California and Iceland where the San Andreas Fault and the Mid-Atlantic Rift exist - visibly or invisibly - alongside human environments; subjects in this series include housing developments, monitoring stations, geologic features and landscapes, coastal roads, and geothermal structures such as greenhouses. The images were shot in color and are suffused with pale tonalities. Prints measure 13 1/2 x16 inches. Also published as a photobook in 2012, available in the library.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Coasts -- California -- Photographs; Documentary Photography -- California; Documentary photography -- Florida; Documentary Photography -- Iceland; Faults (Geology) -- California -- Photographs; Geothermal resources -- Iceland -- Photographs; Immigrants -- Florida; Landscape photography -- Iceland; Landscape photography -- United States; Nature -- effect of human beings on; Rifts (Geology) -- Iceland -- Photographs; Water resources development -- Environmental aspects -- Florida; Wetland ecology -- Florida; California -- Photographs; Everglades (Fla.) -- Photographs; Florida -- Photographs; Florida -- Social conditions; Iceland -- Photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Digital prints; Inkjet prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Belanger, Marion, 1957-
- Everglades, 2001-2004; All prints are signed by the photographer and measure 16 x 13 inches, with images sized 12 1/2 x 10 inches.
  Scope and Contents
  The collection consists of 25 16x13 inch black-and-white photographs taken from 2001 to 2004 by Marion Belanger, documenting the impact of human land use and demand for water on the Florida Everglades. The images show wildlife and natural landscapes as well as the presence and impacts of tourism, agriculture, migrant worker housing, construction, and the activities of the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers and the U.S. Army.
  From the artist's statement:
  "...I had seen the Everglades from the plane – a dark nothingness at night, and by day a flat, often wet, expanse of swampland, punctuated by agricultural fields and housing developments. I was curious to experience the natural landscape, of course, but I was even more interested in the determined efforts of engineers, over many years, to eliminate the swamp for sugarcane fields and development profit. To me it was the dark heart of the state. Once I went there the actual place itself was more extreme than I could have imagined – the park itself like a living museum; miles of water control canals, levees, pumps, and dams; empty spaces, acres of emptiness, vast sugarcane fields, and (mostly gated) housing developments. My working process is not to impose the preconceived, but to embrace the unexpected..."
  The full artist's statement is available in the portfolio box.
  Titles and dates transcribed as they appear on the print versos.
  The Everglades project was supported with a 2002 John Simon Guggenheim Fellowship.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  The photographs in this series were printed in 2018 on an Epson 7800 with Piezography Carbon Ink on Hahnemuhle Photo Rag Ultra Smooth 305 gsm paper.
  - Everglades mural, Clewiston, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0001)
  - Orange grove, Indiantown, 2001 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0002)
  - Water control construction, Kissimmee River, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0003)
  - Great Blue Heron, Everglades National Park Museum, 2003 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0004)
  - Migrant worker housing, Ritta Village, Clewiston, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0005)
  - Easy chairs, Port Mayaca, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0006)
  - Alligator in culvert, Shark Valley, Everglades National Park, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0007)
  - Herbert Hoover Dike, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0008)
  - Subdivision, St. Cloud, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0009)
  - Subdivision, St. Cloud, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0010)
  - Thicket, Everglades National Park, 2001 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0011)
  - Destroyed swamp, US 27, 2001 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0012)
  - Tree root, Everglades National Park, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0013)
  - Painted Road, Big Cypress National Preserve (the Blocks), 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0014)
  - Alligator, Corkscrew Swamp Sanctuary, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0015)
  - Fox, near US 27, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0016)
  - Canal fishing, Canal Point, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0017)
  - Airboat Tours, Tamiami Trail, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0018)
  - US Army, Nike missile site, Everglades National Park, 2004 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0019)
  - Roadside, FL 9336, Homestead, 2001 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0020)
  - Fish carcass, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0021)
  - Corkscrew Swamp Sanctuary, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0022)
  - Water, Everglades National Park, 2001 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0023)
  - Aerial, Clewiston, 2004 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0024)
  - Turner River, Ten Thousand Islands, 2002 (Box 1, Image RL.11615-P-0025)
- Rift / Fault, 2006-2012; 1.0 Linear Feet 1 box 48 color inkjet prints; All prints are signed by the photographer and measure 16 1/2 x 13 inches, with images measuring 13 1/2 x 10 3/4 inches.
  These 48 images were taken between 2006 and 2012 in dramatic geological zones in California and Iceland, and, as in Belanger's previous project on the Everglades, she focuses attention on the dual relationship of landscapes and their impact on humans, and humans and their impact on the environment.
  From the artist's statement: "Rift/Fault is a study of the shifting land-based tectonic edges of the North American Continental Plate in California and Iceland. Rift refers to where the North American Plate meets the Eurasian Plate, along the Mid-Atlantic Rift in Iceland. Fault refers to the San Andreas Fault, where the North American and Pacific Plates meet. Tectonic plates slide along the mantle of our earth, underneath our oceans, our land, our homes. Tectonic plate edges are geologically active - they spread, move, erupt, and tremble. Their behavior is for the most part unpredictable, and wholly uncontainable. And while boundaries upon the land are often contested, politicized, and fought over, tectonic plate edges remain immune to any human efforts of control. I photographed the visual traces (or not) of the tectonic plate edges upon the land, as well the structures and uses of the built landscape upon those edges, allowing for dialogue between the wild and the contained, the fertile and the barren, the geologic and the human. These dichotomies create a visual tension that questions the uneasy relationship between geologic force, and the limits of human intervention."
  Titles and dates are transcribed as they appear on the print versos.
  The photographs in this series were printed in 2019 on an Epson 3880 with archival Epson pigment inks on Hahnemuhle Photo Rag Pearl paper.
  - Fault 52, Point Delgada, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0026)
  - Fault 56, Cars, Mussel Rock Park, Daly City, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0027)
  - Fault 22, Stalled housing development, San Bernardino, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0028)
  - Fault 24, Wind turbines, Desert Hot Springs, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0029)
  - Fault 18, Animal tracks and salt, Salton Sea, 2009 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0030)
  - Fault 15, Concrete wall, San Bernadino, 2009 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0031)
  - Fault 16, Vista, San Bernardino, 2009 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0032)
  - Fault 55, Pacific Ocean, Cape Mendocino, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0033)
  - Fult 50, Beach, North of Point Reyes, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0034)
  - Fault 37, Spa sign, Desert Hot Springs, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0035)
  - Fault 30, Coachella Valley, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0036)
  - Fault 23, Night view, San Bernardino, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0037)
  - Fault 10, Orange fence, Daly City, 2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0038)
  - Fault 26, Lots, Salton Sea, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0039)
  - Fault 53, Tsunami hazard zone, Cape Mendocino, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0040)
    In the inventory, this print is given the alternate title of "Tsunami sign."
  - Fault 28, Cactus farm, Desert Hot Springs, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0041)
  - Fault 45, Earthquake monitor site, Parkfield, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0042)
  - Fault 11, House, Daly City, 2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0043)
  - Fault 6, Mussel Rock Park, Daly City, 2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0044)
  - Fault 43, Cracked retaining wall, Hollister, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0045)
  - Fault 19, Oranges, San Bernardino County, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0046)
  - Fault 36, Plastic litter, Desert Hot Springs, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0047)
  - Fault 3, Wallace Creek, Carrizo Plain National Monument, 2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0048)
  - Fault 54, Fog, Shelter Cove Road, 2012 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0049)
  - Rift 31, Parking lot, Route 1 near Hveragerði, 2007 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0050)
  - Rift 8, Hot lava, Leirhnjukur, 2006 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0051)
  - Rift 25, Excavated chimney, Heimaey, 2007 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0052)
  - Rift 22, New trees, Landbrotshólar Pseudocrater Region, 2006 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0053)
  - Rift 23, Borehole, Nesjavellir Power Station, 2006 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0054)
  - Rift 18, Hot pool, Laugarvatan, 2006 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0055)
  - Rift 62, Mineral rich water, Svartsengi Power Station, 2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0056)
  - Rift 12, Lava field, near Volcano Hekla, 2006 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0057)
  - Rift 1, Tectonic plate edges, Thingvellir, 2006 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0058)
  - Rift 11, Rauðhólar Pseudocrater remnant, Reykjavik, 2006 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0059)
  - Rift 34, New construction, Hveragerði, 2007 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0060)
  - Rift 42, Houses, Heimaey, 2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0061)
  - Rift 26, Volcanic excavation site, Heimaey, 2007 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0062)
  - Rift 63, Geysir, Haukadular, 2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0063)
  - Rift 48, Geothermal greenhouse, Reykholt, 2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0064)
  - Rift 32, Fish farm, Husavik, 2007 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0065)
  - Rift 27, Geothermal plant surveillance camera, Reykjanes Peninsula, 2007 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0066)
  - Rift 21, Turf house, Hella, 2006 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0067)
  - Rift 20, Geothermal pipes, Nesjavellir Plant, 2006 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0068)
  - Rift 4, Boiling mud, Krafla, 2006 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0069)
  - Rift 64, Earth crevice, Hveragerði, 2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0070)
  - Rift 12, Iceberg, Jökulsárlón, 2006 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0071)
  - Rift 29, Volcanic excavation site, Heimaey, 2007 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0072)
  - Rift 51, Varma River, Hveragerði, 2011 (Box 2, Image RL.11615-P-0073)